<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.4.3">Jekyll</generator>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
<link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
<updated>2017-05-11T14:31:47-04:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/</id>
<subtitle>a miscellany</subtitle>
<entry>
<title>Luddism</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/11/Luddism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luddism" />
<published>2017-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</published>
<updated>2017-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/2017/05/11/Luddism</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/05/11/Luddism.html">&lt;p&gt;title: “New Wave computing: Indexing in the pre-Internet utopia of the 80s”
layout: post
—
&lt;strong&gt;Epistemological Status:&lt;/strong&gt; Mostly anecdotal self-experimentation that I happen to have strong feelings about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The internet is extremely addictive. It gets in the way of my work, and I suspect it gets in the way of yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My primary computer-based job these days is book indexing. I take a book, usually from an academic press, read it carefully, consider the interrelation of concepts, and produce a standard back-of-the-book index. It’s difficult intellectual work, and it requires a lot of concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, I find it hard to concentrate while sitting in front of a computer.  I’ve tried over the years to deal with this in four ways:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Don’t use a computer.
2) Use a computer, but physically disable the internet.
3) Use a computer, but take ADD medication.
4) Use a computer, but use mindfulness techniques to stay on task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I reflect on these possibilities with all of my hobbies (programming, philosophy, etc), and I think they’ve all led my thoughts in interesting directions.  In this post I’ll focus exclusively on how they’ve changed my indexing habits over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-use-a-computer&quot;&gt;Don’t use a computer&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Can indexing be done without a computer? It used to be. Back when we got started indexing at Twin Oaks, it was done on 3x5 index cards, which were then collated and typed up on a typewriter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That sounded cool to me, so one day I gathered up a bunch of cards, a box with alphabetic dividers, and a pen, and gave it a go. After an hour or so (which I’ll admit is far from being a fair attempt), I decided this was not going to work, for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Searching is tedious: Did I already create a card for a certain topic? If so, I have to spend time locating it. If not, I have to spend time checking for similar wordings. On a computer, I can search instantly for old entries.
2) Collation is tedious: After having done all the work of writing out all these cards, you &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; have to go back through them (hundreds or thousands of them) and type them into a computer. If I just started on the computer, this obviously wouldn’t be necessary.
3) Writing is sloowwwww. I type fast! I appreciate the slowness of handwriting for many things – notetaking, letters, etc, but I don’t need to slow down when indexing! I need to go faster!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so, I think I need a computer, at least for indexing. But maybe your job doesn’t!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;use-a-computer-but-physically-disable-the-internet&quot;&gt;Use a computer, but physically disable the internet&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think this is the best solution for most people. Ask youself: Is there any part of this job that I can do without the internet? If so, you will definitely be served by setting up an internet-free work area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a number of bad ways to do this: Namely, any of those crappy bits of software you can download that claim to prevent you from accessing certain websites at certain times. If you’re smart enough to install some software, you’re smart enough to disable it. &lt;em&gt;Don’t trust your future self&lt;/em&gt;. Future self isn’t a rational forward-thinking person. Future self is hungry, bored, and low on willpower. Make it difficult for future self.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How? Well, I’m one of the few people who still seems to use a desktop these days, so I just periodically rip out the network card.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t have a desktop? Well, install a second copy of your operating system and don’t install your network drivers. I usually install an old version of Linux that doesn’t work with whatever built-in network card I have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly, I think you should get a work desktop if possible. Because my job is just to work with plain text, I can use a decade-old machine that someone was about to recycle. I suspect many people would be well-served by such a setup: a good portion of many people’s jobs involves reading documents and writing text. You don’t need a new computer to do that. Instead, build a work computer, install the minimum set of necessary applications, and then rip out the network card. Once you’re done working on it, transfer the files you need onto a usb drive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, for god’s sake, don’t bring your smartphone anywhere near. I get that some people claim to need them, but I suspect most of them are wrong. Just get an old brick phone instead, at least for work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;internet-free-work-computerstill-distracted&quot;&gt;Internet-free work computer…STILL DISTRACTED&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe I’m an extreme case, or I’m just especially repulsed by the distractable era we live in, but even an internet-free computer isn’t enough for me. I need it to feel like the mid 80s. I need a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.reddit.com/r/retrobattlestation&quot;&gt;retro battlestation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, that means: text-only with huge-ass fonts. Like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No Windows. No pdf reader. No music. No videos. Just me, plain text, and peace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most indexers these days have two programs running at all times: a pdf reader and dedicated indexing software. For a long time, I thought both were necesary, which prevented me from having a truly peaceful retro experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But one day, I noticed that the indexing software was able to import from/export to a plain-text file. I checked out the format, and it was dead simple: entry name, tab, subentry name, tab, page numer. My text editor &lt;a href=&quot;www.vim.org&quot;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;(?) already lets me do most of what people like about the indexing software: search, auto-complete, keystroke recording to do repetitive tasks, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the indexing software does of importance now is handling the minutae of formatting details in the final copy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what about the PDF reader? For this I decided to ditch the computer, print the document, and use a highlighter. This is slower than just making a single pass through the document on the computer, but it allows me to work and think outside and take a break between computer-bound concept-crunching sessions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;advantages-of-new-wave-computing&quot;&gt;Advantages of New Wave computing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In all likelyhood, you’ll work faster. I certainly do, since I spend less time dicking around on reddit. But even if you don’t, even if these different tools slow you down, you’ll still experience the primary advantages of working on a retro battlestation: mental calm and higher quality work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait, there’s more. Are you like me? You probably are. You know a thing or two about programming.  I probably don’t need to tell you that plain-text files are holy to programmers and that legions of tools exist for working with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, sometimes a client will be like, “Hey, I’d like comic strips to be indexed like this: NAME (AUTHOR) (GENRE). But then later, they’re like, “SIKE! I want NAME (GENRE, AUTHOR).” My coworkers used to spend hours fixing this kind of crap by hand. If you’re working with plain text, this is fixable with a single line of code in a program called &lt;em&gt;grep&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a second example, indexes are full of entries which mirror each other, like: “Gulf War, feminism and” and “Feminists, response to Gulf War by”.  Usually people check by hand that these entries line up exactly.  I wrote a program that searches for similar entries like this using a basic text-matching algorithm, reporting entries that are both similar enough and differing in pages. Can’t do that in an indexing program!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mindfulness-practices&quot;&gt;Mindfulness practices&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once upon a time, I lived in a Buddhist monastery. I meditated for thousands of hours. When I came home, I could sometimes engage with computers without being distracted, but mostly I decided it was still too difficult.  Your mileage may vary, but I take this as a sign that computers (especially the internet) are a radically different beast compared to all distracting phenomena in human history.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;add-drugs&quot;&gt;ADD drugs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I dunno. I’m stubborn. If I have ADD, it’s mild. I hear reports of people with ADD struggling to function at all, which is not my experience. Certainly, the times I’ve medicated, I’ve found myself able to engage in amazing feats of concentration. But ADD drugs are also highly addictive and side-effectful. I encourage people with ADD to treat for it, but I also think that most first-world people in the 21st century are neurotypical and just struggling to deal with the highly atypical cognitive universe we live in these days.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
<summary>title: “New Wave computing: Indexing in the pre-Internet utopia of the 80s”layout: post—Epistemological Status: Mostly anecdotal self-experimentation that I happen to have strong feelings about.</summary>
</entry>
<entry>
<title>Practical Memory Palaces: Consequentialism</title>
<link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/15/Consequentialism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Practical Memory Palaces: Consequentialism" />
<published>2017-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</published>
<updated>2017-04-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/15/Consequentialism</id>
<content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/15/Consequentialism.html">&lt;p&gt;If you look around on the internet, you’ll notice a bunch of people using memory palaces for a bunch of useless crap, interspersed with wild claims about how memory palaces can revolutionize education. This gives the impression that memory palaces are for weirdos. I’d like to fix that by giving you an concrete example of my reading workflow, and how I integrate memory palaces into my normal notetaking procedure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a philosophy student, I read a lot of books and articles that I’d like to remember.  Just yesterday, I decided to read the &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/consequentialism/&quot;&gt;consequentialism entry&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/consequentialism/&quot;&gt;Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;.  Maybe you have similar interests – perhaps you’re a science nerd or a yoga nerd or a Buddhist nerd. Hopefully you will find it easy to translate my example here to your interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;about-consequentialism&quot;&gt;About Consequentialism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consequentialism is the name given to a broad range of ethical theories that consider the &lt;strong&gt;consequences&lt;/strong&gt; of one’s actions as the basis of morality. Among professional twenty-first century philosophers, it’s the most popular ethical stance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article opens with an analysis of utilitarianism: The classical consequentialist theory as formulated by Bentham, Mill, and Sidgwick. It’s often summarized as something like: “An action is good to the extent that it causes the greatest pleasure and the least pain for the greatest number of people.”  The analysis breaks down this seemingly-simple formulation into a number of distinct claims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After finishing the article, I noticed that this breakdown of the parts of utilitarianism was the key to understanding the rest: every section that followed considered some part of utilitarianism and how contemporary consequentialists accept, reject, or modify those parts. Knowing this list would help me to think about consequentialism in a structured way long after reading the article.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in what follows, we’ll make a memory palace for the subclaims of classical utilitarianism by mentally walking through your house (or any building with many rooms that you know well) and “placing” things that remind you of the list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-list&quot;&gt;The List&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;sidepic&quot; src=&quot;/assets/scolding.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Okay, so, mentally place yourself at the entrance to your building of choice. Visualize the door. Imagine there’s a &lt;strong&gt;babysitter&lt;/strong&gt; standing outside telling some kids about the &lt;strong&gt;consequences&lt;/strong&gt; of their horrible misdeeds. Try and use all your senses: see him gesticulating, hear him rattling off the list of “if you do this, I’ll call your mother!”, etc.  Okay, that’s element one on the list. It represents the obvious first part of utilitarianism: it considers consequences (as opposed to the circumstances around the act or the “nature of the act”, for instance)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;sidepic&quot; src=&quot;/assets/keanu.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Walk in the door. Now, imagine an &lt;strong&gt;actor&lt;/strong&gt;, and place them somewhere obvious in the room, acting out something. I picked Keanu Reeves, and in my memory palace, he’s banging on a grain silo. Again, try to use all your senses when imagining this. This actor acting reminds us of the second subclaim: that utilitarianism considers the &lt;strong&gt;actual&lt;/strong&gt; consequences, as opposed to “forseen, forseeable, intended, or likely” ones. If you’re mechanically inclined, I think an &lt;strong&gt;actuator&lt;/strong&gt; would be a better choice for this point, since the pronunciation is more similar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;sidepic&quot; src=&quot;/assets/director.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Pick an adjacent room or another large section of this room to go to. Place a &lt;strong&gt;director&lt;/strong&gt; in a director’s chair directing a movie (maybe starring the actor in the previous location). This reminds us that utilitarianism is &lt;strong&gt;direct&lt;/strong&gt; – it considers the direct consequences of the act itself as opposed to, say, the motive.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Again, new room/new part of room. Plop down a colossal set of boxes/safes/drawers containing all your &lt;strong&gt;valuables&lt;/strong&gt;. Make them overflowing, of varying kinds, etc. Make sure they’re valuable, and not just junk. This reminds us that utilitarianism is &lt;strong&gt;evaluative&lt;/strong&gt; – i.e, it considers the value of the consequences, not other “non-evaluative features.” The article uses the example of a consequentialist who arbitrarily chooses “the number of goats in Texas” as the only consequences to consider for any given action.  This is absurd, and importantly, it is not a consequence that anyone (except maybe…Texan goat conservationists) conceivably values. You can stick a goat in the box of valuables if that helps you remember.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Next room. Place an archetypal &lt;strong&gt;hedonist&lt;/strong&gt; somewhere – mine is obscene, injecting themselves with various needles, holding a cup of coffee, and having sex, all at the same time. The hedonist reminds us that utilitarianism only cares about &lt;strong&gt;pleasure&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;pain&lt;/strong&gt;, to the exclusion of all other possible valuations: that is, utilitarianism is hedonic.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;sidepic&quot; src=&quot;/assets/optimus.jpg&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Next!  &lt;strong&gt;OPTIMUS PRIME&lt;/strong&gt; is hanging out here, reminding us that utilitarianism is about &lt;strong&gt;optimal&lt;/strong&gt; or maximal good, as opposed to merely satisfactory good. That is, it’s less good for us to give a tiny portion of our money to charity than to give as much as possible (as much as will optimize our lifelong charitability, accounting for psychological burnout, for instance).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Onward. The entire room is littered with machine &lt;strong&gt;parts&lt;/strong&gt;: engines, tires, tools, etc. All of them are being combined into one big machine. This reminds us that utilitarianism is interested in adding up the &lt;strong&gt;parts&lt;/strong&gt; of the consequences into one sum (this much pain here, this much pleasure here, etc), as opposed to, say, considering each individual’s pain/pleasure separately.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ahoy. A cashier is in this room, &lt;strong&gt;totaling&lt;/strong&gt; up the cost of each part being used in the previous room. This reminds us that utilitarianism considers the “total net good in the consequences”, not, say, the “average net good per person”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Whoa. A huge floating orb is in this room, containing an entire &lt;strong&gt;universe&lt;/strong&gt;. You can see all the galaxies and shit swimming around in it. Pretty sweet. This reminds us that utilitarianism is &lt;strong&gt;universal&lt;/strong&gt; – it considers the pain and pleasure of “&lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; people or sentient beings.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;img class=&quot;sidepic&quot; src=&quot;/assets/equality.png&quot; align=&quot;right&quot; /&gt;Almost there. Someone has walked through here and put hundreds of those blue and yellow &lt;strong&gt;equality&lt;/strong&gt; stickers everywhere. This reminds us that utilitarianism considers each person equally – “benefits to one person matter &lt;em&gt;just as much&lt;/em&gt; as similar benefits to any other person.”&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;FINAL ROOM YAY. Weirdly, everything in the room has been painted in only &lt;strong&gt;neutral&lt;/strong&gt; colors: browns, greys, light greens and tans. You are disturbed. This reminds us that utilitarianism is &lt;strong&gt;agent-neutral&lt;/strong&gt;: that is, “which consequences are better…does not depend on…the perspective of the agent.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;THE END! Now would be a good time to close your eyes and run through your freshly-minted memory palace once more to solidify it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Done?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweet.  Now you know the various claims made by utilitarianism, and you will be able to better consider the strengths and weaknesses of it: Is agent neutrality even possible? Are pleasure and pain &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; simple enough that we can calculate with them? Etc. Ideally, if you’ve never heard of consequentialism or utilitarianism, you’ll now have a new mental framework to consider the rightness or wrongness of your own actions/political beliefs/etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;possible-troublequestions&quot;&gt;Possible trouble/questions:&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I ran out of rooms! Ahh!:&lt;/strong&gt; Well, you can always put more stuff in each room, or you can be creative and add an imaginary addition to your location. Or, just put a magic portal in your last available room that leads you to &lt;em&gt;another&lt;/em&gt; location you know well.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How long will I remember this?:&lt;/strong&gt; It depends on how memorable you made the images, and how much you care about the subject matter. I’d say on average you’d have the information available for a week without review. With a few reviews every now and then, it’s easy to retain the material indefinitely.  My partner still remembers a weird list of random objects I helped her memorize three years ago, and she never reviews it on her own. For me, I think about ethics a lot, so I’m inclined to spontaneously review the material. If I’m memorizing something I may only think about infrequently, I make a note in a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.samuraimindonline.com/samurai-notebooks-of-the-mind/&quot;&gt;review notebook&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://apps.ankiweb.net&quot;&gt;Anki&lt;/a&gt; to remind myself to walk through the memory palace at a later date.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</content>
<summary>If you look around on the internet, you’ll notice a bunch of people using memory palaces for a bunch of useless crap, interspersed with wild claims about how memory palaces can revolutionize education. This gives the impression that memory palaces are for weirdos. I’d like to fix that by giving you an concrete example of my reading workflow, and how I integrate memory palaces into my normal notetaking procedure.</summary>
</entry>
</feed>
